Register of the Donald Marquand Dozer Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS FILE, circa 1930-1980
  - Review of David McCullough, The Path Between the Seas: The Creation of the Panama Canal, 1870-1914, and Wayne D. Bray, The Common Law Zone in Panama: A Case Study in Reception, Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, Notes, typescript, cards, 1978 March (Folder 22)
  - "You Can Help Save the Canal But Time's Running Out," Spotlight, Mimeographed copy of article, 1979 February 19 (Folder 23)
  - Review of Truman R. Clark, Puerto Rico and the United States, The Americas, Serial issue and letter, 1979, July. 1978-1979 (Folder 24)
  - "Symbiosis of Greater America: A History of Inter-American Relations," This manuscript is a synthesis of two earlier manuscripts: "The Challenge of Our Latin American Policy," and "The State of Greater America"., circa 1980
    - General
      - Correspondence, 1962-1974 (Folder 25)
      - Grant applications
        - National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH), Applications and letters, 1967-1973 (Folder 26)
        - University of California, Santa Barbara, Forms and letters, 1978-1980 (Folder 27)
      - Miscellaneous. Fragments and charts (Folder 28)
    - Table of Contents and Preface (Folder 29)
    - 1. Beginnings of Inter-American Relations (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - 2. Emergence of the United States of America (Folder 2)
    - 3. Definition of United States Boundaries (Folder 3)
    - 4. American Interaction for Independence (Folder 4)
    - 5. The United States, Precedent Maker (Folder 5)
    - 6. The Monroe Doctrine (Folder 6)
    - 7. Early Attempts at Pan-American Cooperation (Folder 7)
    - 8. Basic Boundary Agreements in South America (Folder 8)
    - 9. Borderland Rivalries in Northern South America (Folder 9)
    - 10. United States-Mexican Relations (Folder 10)
    - 11. Boundary Limits in Middle and North America (Folder 11)
    - 12. Expanding Cultural Dimensions (Folder 12)
    - 13. Transportation and Communication (Folder 13)
    - 14. Organization of Greater America (Folder 14)
    - 15. [Early Threats to Pan-Americanism] (Folder 15)
    - 16. A Isthmian Canal (Folder 16)
    - 17. United States Imperialism (Folder 17)
    - 18. Inter-American Boundary Problems since South America, 1890 (Folder 18)
    - 19. Inter-American Boundary Problems since Middle America, 1890 (Folder 19)
    - 20. The United States and its Neighbors in the Twentieth Century (Folder 20)
    - 21. The Good Neighbor Era (Folder 21)
    - 22. Greater America and World War II (Folder 22)
    - 23. Challenge of International Communism (Folder 23)
    - 24. Economic Pan Americanism (Folder 24)
    - 25. Alliance for Progress (Folder 25)
    - 26. Alliance for Progress in Operation (Folder 26)
    - 27. Broadening Inter-American Horizons (Folder 27)
    - 28. The Politics of Control (Folder 28)
    - 29. The Common Law Versus the Civil Law (Box 150, Folder 1)
    - 30. Positivism as an Inter-American Force (Folder 2)
    - 31. The State of Greater America (Folder 3)
    - 32. The Prospects for Inter-American Cooperation (Folder 4)
- U.S. GOVERNMENT SERVICE FILE, 1937-1973
  Reports, memoranda, personnel materials, correspondence, clippings, conference materials, notes, speech transcripts, press releases, budgets and other miscellany. Arranged by department, then by physical form (NOTE: Materials related to Dr. Dozer's involvement in the World War II diplomatic papers publication controversy are in a separate series, U.S. GOVERNMENT SERVICE FILE-B, described below).
  - General. Dozer personnel material, excluding that which relates to his dismissal (SEE: U.S. GOVERNMENT SERVICE FILE-B/Dozer, Donald M./Personnel material)
    - General, Regulations, legal brief, notes, 1946-1955 (Box 44, Folder 1)
    - Applications, Includes statements and job descriptions, 1937-1956 (Folder 2-3)
    - Correspondence and memoranda, Includes correspondence with former employees relating to conditions within the State Department, 1937-1958 (Folder 4-6)
    - Miscellaneous forms, Position description and personnel action forms, 1944-1952 (Folder 7)
    - Performance evaluations, 1944-1952 (Folder 8)
  - Office of Strategic Services, Division of Special Information, Latin American Section, Research and Analysis Branch
    - Memoranda, Primarily requests for information from other government agencies, 1941 October-1943 February (Folder 9)
    - Reports, 1941-1943
      - General
        - General, Relates to Latin American-international relations, specifically Latin American attitudes toward World War II and the Axis. Short typescripts and holographs, circa 1942 (Folder 10)
        - A.I.C. reports (analyses of Latin American newspaper articles), Relates primarily to Puerto Rico, but also includes Venezuela, Cuba and the Dominican Republic. Typescripts and holographs, 1942-1943 (Folder 11)
        - Interviews (Folder 12)
          - "Personalities and Conditions in the Dominican Republic," Typescript summary of interview with Dr. J.I. Jimenes Guillon, 1942 November 6
          - "The Trujillo Regime in the Dominican Republic," Typescript summary of interview with Avra M. Warren, American Minister to the Dominican Republic, 1942 December 3
          - "Present Political Conditions in Venezuela," 1942 december 15. Typescript summary of interview with Juan Oropesa (writer for Caracas newspaper Ahora)
        - Miscellaneous. Printed and non-printed background material, 1940-1942 (Folder 13)
      - "Short Guide to Cuba," Typescript, apparently intended for briefing military or other personnel, undated (Folder 14)
      - "Short Guide to Haiti," Draft consisting of both typescript and holograph sections, undated (Folder 15)
      - "Elements of Insecurity in Colombia," Typescript report, 1941 October 21 (Folder 16)
      - "Present Political Insecurities in Panama," Also includes follow-up report entitled, "Special Sitation Report--Panama". Typescripts with cover memorandum, 1941 October-November (Box 45, Folder 1)
      - "Elements of Insecurity in Venezuela," Typescript drafts and memoranda, 1941 November 12 (Folder 2)
      - "The Union Nacional Sinarquista of Mexico," Memorandum of interview, mimeographed OSS reports, pamphlets distributed by the Union Nacional Sinarquista, notes and a typescript report, 1941 December 1941-1943 (Folder 3)
      - "Laxity in Enforcement of Surveillance Measures by the Dominican Government," Typescript report, 1942 March 5 (Folder 4)
      - "Strategic Significance of Food Shortages in the Caribbean," (Report #36). Typescript with cover memorandum, 1942 July 10 (Folder 5)
      - "Existing Mechanisms for Handling the Caribbean Food Problem,", 1942-1943
        - General. Memoranda, letters, including typescript copy of a letter from President Roosevelt to Sumner Welles, reports, statistical charts and bulletins, notes, press release, and a pamphlet (Folder 6-7)
        - Drafts (Folder 8)
          - (Report #44). Typescript with cover memorandum, 1942 October 10
          - (Report #95). Typescript with editor's marks, 1942 November 19
          - (Report #114). Mimeographed final copy, 1943 February 10
      - "Current Religious Difficulties in Haiti," Typescript with cover memorandum, 1942 March 3 (Folder 9)
      - "Pro-Democratic Labor Activity in Colombia," Typescript with cover memorandum, 1942 March 4 (Folder 10)
      - "The Presidential Campaign in Colombia," Typescript with cover memorandum, 1942 March 28 (Folder 11)
      - "Present Anti-Democratic Forces in Cuba," Typescript with cover memorandum, 1942 June 3 (Folder 12)
      - "Crisis in the Cuban Government," Typescript with cover memorandum, 1942 August 7 (Folder 13)
      - "Short Guide to the Dominican Republic," Typescript draft with cover memorandum, 1942 September 23 (Folder 14)
      - "The Dominican Republic in Hemispheric Security," Typescript outline, 1942 November (Folder 15)
  - Administration Became Foreign Economic Administration, 1943 Sept
    - General
      - General, Chart, statement, personnel assignments, budgets, 1943-1944 (Folder 16)
      - Food programs. Pamphlet, reprints, statements, charts, reports (Soy Flour Association materials related to the use of soya in food programs), 1944 (Folder 17)
    - Administrative material. Requisitions, surplus reports, memoranda, and letters
      - 1943 February-October (Folder 18-22)
      - 1943 November-1944 September (Box 46, Folder 1-7)
    - Reports
      - "Caribbean Organizes its War Economy,", 1941-1943
        - General. Memoranda, letters, charts, pamphlet (Folder 8)
        - Draft sections and notes (Folder 9)
      - "Report to Congress on Lend-Lease Operations." Includes "Reverse Lend-Lease Aid from the British Commonwealth of Nations". Printed reports, 1943 March 11-1944 May 22 (Folder 10-12)
  - State Department
    - General
      - General
        - General, Press releases, directories, memoranda, regulations, newsletters, speech transcript (John M. Butler), letters from Bryton Barron and Senator Karl Mundt, notes and statements by Dr. Dozer, 1953-1963 (Folder 13)
        - Clippings, 1953-1973 (Box 47, Folder 1)
        - Directories, 1944-1950 (Folder 2)
      - Organization and Administration. Clippings, press releases, hearing transcript, memoranda, report. Includes some Hoover Commission material, primarily relating to the Office of Intelligence Research, 1947-1949 (Folder 3)
      - Security
        - General
          - General
            - Non-printed material
              - General. Press releases, letters of reference and statements by Dr. Dozer, including one given to the FBI regarding his supervisor, 1946-1954 (Folder 4)
              - Nikoloric, Leonard A., Untitled and unpublished article relating to the Loyalty Program. Correspondence and two typescript drafts, 1949-1962 (Folder 5)
            - Printed material, Clippings, 1947-1968 (Folder 6)
          - Otepka (Otto) case
            - General, Flyer, newsletter, letters, clippings, and a script, possibly for the film described in the following correspondence, 1967-1972 (Folder 7)
            - Correspondence, Relates to the production of a film by Raymond Wagoner (SEE ALSO: PANAMA CANAL FILE/Citizens groups-specific canal committees/Emergency Committee to Save the U.S. Canal Zone/Correspondence), 1966-1968 (Folder 8)
        - Dozer (Donald) Loyalty Review
          - Affidavits, 1949 July-September (Folder 9)
          - Correspondence, 1943-1950
            - General
              - General. Includes notes (Folder 10)
              - Letters of support. Includes affidavits
                - Armstrong, Sinclair (Folder 11)
                - Armstrong, W. Park, Jr.
                - Baxter, James P.
                - Braden, Spruille
                - Briggs, Ellis O.
                - Bunche, Ralph
                - Curlin, Claud D.
                - Dreier, John C.
                - Dunn, William E.
                - Eddy, William A.
                - Evans, Allan
                - Griffith, Ernest S.
                - Howard, John B.
                - Hussey, Roland D. (Folder 12)
                - James, Lt. Col. Preston
                - Langer, William L.
                - Lester, W. Stewart, Jr.
                - McSweeney, John (M.C.)
                - Morse, Wayne (Senator)
                - Nikoloric, Leonard A.
                - Read, Conyers
                - Secrest, Robert T. (M.C.)
                - Shera, Jesse
                - Spaeth, Carl
                - Wilson, John A.
                - Woodward, Robert F.
            - Loyalty Board, Darrell St. Claire, Acting Chairman. Includes final copy of Dozer affidavit, 1949 June-November (Folder 13)
    - Division of Research for American Republics (DRA) (Transferred from the Office of American Republics Affairs to the Office of Intelligence Research in but its basic function remained unchanged), February 1947
      - General (predominantly administrative materials). Notes, lists and directories, agenda, budgets, press releases, report, letter, statements by Dr. Dozer. Includes "N.I.S. Control Book," apparently a log of project activity
        - undated (Folder 14)
        - 1948-1950 (Box 48, Folder 1)
      - Conferences
        - Conference on Problems of War and Peace, Mexico City, Press releases, reports, clippings, wire report, printed reports, and a speech transcript (Ellis O. Briggs), 1944-1945 (Folder 2)
        - Second Latin American Intelligence Conference, Panama Canal Zone, 1948 January (Folder 3-4)
          - General. Conference materials
          - Reports and memoranda. Typescript and mimeographed materials, 1947-1948
        - Ninth International Conference of American States, Bogota, Colombia
          - General, 1947-1948
            - General. Predominantly Colombian newspapers
              - El Espectador, April 4-7 (Folder 5)
              - Jornada, March 30-April 7 (Folder 6-7)
              - El Liberal, March 30-April 7 (Folder 8-9)
              - Semana, April 3 (Folder 10)
              - El Siglo, March 30-April 7 (Box 49, Folder 1-4)
              - Star and Herald (Panama), April 13 (Folder 5)
              - El Tiempo (Folder 6-8)
                - March 29-April 3
                - April 4-9 (Box 50, Folder 1-2)
              - Vanguardia del Pueblo (Communist party publication), April 5 (Folder 3)
            - Pre-conference preparatory materials, 1947-1948
              - General
                - Non-printed material. (Folder 4)
                - Printed material. (Folder 5)
              - Executive Committee on Economic Foreign Policy. Reports, proposals and recommendations, memoranda, minutes
                - 1947 (Folder 6)
                - 1948
            - Post-conference evaluative materials. Clipping about Dr. Dozer, letters, memoranda, miscellany, a typescript copy of a Colombian communist party handbill, a radio address by Norman Armour, a mimeographed report by the State Dept., "U.S. Opinion on the Achievements of the Bogota Conference," and a printed report by the U.S. House of Representatives. Includes descriptions of the interruption of the conference by riots following the murder of Jorge Eliecer Gaitan, 1948 April-September (Folder 9)
          - Administration, 1948
            - General
              - General. Conference program, mimeographed statements relating to security regulations, travel arrangements, communications procedures, financial arrangements, directories, list of general reference materials (Folder 10-11)
              - Lists of delegates and documents (Folder 12)
              - Miscellaneous. Identification card, maps and guide books, certificate, and other miscellany (Box 51, Folder 1)
            - Memoranda (Folder 2)
            - Orders of the day (agenda) (Folder 3)
            - Reports. Official daily newsletter (S) (Folder 4-5)
          - Committees, 1948 March 30-April 9
            - General
              - General. List describing different committees, proposal, report, daily and weekly summaries (Folder 6)
              - Committee on Initiatives. Resolutions, minutes, proposals. English (E) and Spanish (S) (Folder 7)
              - U.S. Delegation committees
                - General. Minutes, reports, memoranda (Folder 8)
                - Committee IV: Economics (SEE below). Transcripts of discussions (Folder 9)
                - Steering Committee. Minutes (Folder 10)
            - Committee I: Organic Pact
              - General
                - General. Draft pacts, amendments and other proposals, memoranda, notes (Folder 11)
                - Minutes (S)(E) (Folder 12)
              - Subcommittees (A, B, C)
                - Minutes (S) (Folder 13)
                - Position papers and reports (Folder 14)
            - Committee II: Organic Pact and Specialized Organizations
              - General. Minutes (S)(E), resolutions (Folder 15)
              - Subcommittees (A, B, C). Minutes (S)(E) (Folder 16)
            - Committee III: Pacific Settlement Treaty and Collective Defense
              - General. Minutes (S)(E), report by U.S. Delegation (Folder 17)
              - Subcommittees (A, B). Minutes (S)(E), proposals (Folder 18)
            - Committee IV: Economic Matters
              - General
                - General. Proposals, resolutions, position papers and speeches, press release (S)(E)
                - Minutes (S)(E) (Folder 3)
              - Subcommittees. Mimeographed copies of minutes (S)(E) (Folder 4)
            - Committee V: Social Matters
              - General
                - General. Motions, drafts, reports, memorandum, resolutions, position papers (Folder 5)
                - Minutes (S)(E) (Folder 6)
              - Subcommittees (A, B, C). Minutes (E)(S) (Folder 7)
            - Committee VI: Juridico-Political Matters
              - General. Minutes (E)(S), notes (Folder 8)
              - Subcommittees (A, B, C). Statement, position papers, press releases, proposals, minutes (S)(E), notes. Includes typescript drafts of declarations on human rights (Folder 9)
          - Plenary sessions, 1948 March 30-April 8
            - General. Notes (Folder 10)
            - (Inaugural session) Transcripts of speeches by Mariano Ospina Perez (E)(S) and Joao Neves da Fontoura (E) and Portuguese (P), March 30 (Folder 11)
            - Notes, minutes and transcripts of speeches by Laureano Gomez (E)(S), Juvenal Hernandez Jaque (S), Byron Price (S) and Jaime Torres Bodet (E)(S), March 31 (Folder 12)
            - Notes, press releases, minutes, and transcripts of speeches by Juan Atillio Bramuglia (S) and George C. Marshall (E), April 1 (Folder 13)
            - Notes, minutes, and transcripts of speeches given by John J. McCloy (E), Javier Paz Campero (S) and Cesar A. Vasconsellos (S), April 5 (Folder 14)
            - Notes, minutes, and transcripts of speeches by Carlos Lozano y Lozano (S)(E) and Armando Revoredo Iglesia (S), April 6 (Folder 15)
            - Notes, minutes and transcript of speech given by Guillermo Belt (S), April 8 (Folder 16)
          - Statements and Acts, 1948 April-May
            - General. Press releases (U.S. Delegation) (Folder 17)
            - Charter of the Organization of the American States (Folder 18)
            - Economic Agreement of Bogota
            - Final Act of Bogota
            - Inter-American Convention on the Granting of Political Rights to Women
      - Memoranda and correspondence, Relates to specific projects as well as general divisional function. Includes correspondence with Spruille Braden and John Lockwood, 1941-1951 (Box 53, Folder 1-3)
      - Reports
        - General
          - General
            - General, Notes, outlines, fragments. Includes materials developed by Dr. Dozer for staff presentations, 1947-1948 (Folder 4)
            - Short reports (three or fewer pages, and some fragments) relating primarily to Latin American foreign relations, Outline, charts, lists. Includes mimeographed summary of division research activities for february 1947, 1945-1949 (Folder 5)
          - "Diplomatic Representatives of the United States in Latin America," Memorandum and notes, undated (Folder 6)
          - "United States Military Aid to Latin America," Holograph, undated (Folder 7)
          - "Weekly Analysis of Shortwave News and Propaganda Concerning Latin America," Mimeographed copy, 1943 august 10 (Folder 8)
          - "The Status of Inter-American Pacts of Peace, Security and Mutual Guarantee," Typescript, 1944 september 30 (Folder 9)
          - "Relations of the Other American Republics with Spain," Typescript, 1944 november 28 (Folder 10)
          - "Restrictions on Exercise of Political Functions by the Pan American Union," Typescript draft, final copy and memorandum, 1944 december 29 (Folder 11)
          - "Development and Results of the Good Neighbor Policy: Basis of Inter-American Cooperation," Typescript, circa 1945 (Folder 12)
          - "German Missions in the Other American Republics," Typescript copy, 1945 June 29 (Folder 13)
          - "Summary of Issues and Trends in the Other American Republics," Typescript section of longer report, with cover memorandum, 1946 august 23 (Folder 14)
          - "A Survey of National Minorities in Foreign Countries," Section IV: "The Other American Republics," Typescript, 1946 december 3 (Folder 15)
          - "Soviet Policy and Objectives in the Other American Republics," Mimeographed preliminary version, 1946 december 31 (Folder 16)
          - "Asiatics in the Other American Republics," Typescript and memoranda, 1947 february 25 (Folder 17)
          - "Critical Focal Points - Near and Middle East," Typescript, 1948 january 16 (Folder 18)
          - "America and the Hungarian Revolt of 1848-1849," (Division of Research for Europe) Mimeographed copy, 1948 february 25 (Folder 19)
          - "Report on the Status of Human Rights in the Other American Republics," Memoranda only, 1947 october-1948 March (Folder 20)
          - "Thumb-nail Estimates of the Combustibility of the Political Situation in each of the OAR excepting Argentina and Uruguay," Typescript, 1948 April 23 (Folder 21)
          - "Kossuth's Reception in America, 1851-1852," (Division of Research for Europe). Mimeographed copy, 1948 April 30 (Folder 22)
          - "Uncooperation within United States Agencies," Memoranda and typescript draft compilations of specific incidents, 1949 february (Folder 23)
          - "Communism in Latin America," Outline, notes, memoranda. Includes comments on a Library of Congress report on this subject, 1948-1949 (Folder 24)
          - "Income Taxes in Latin America," Mimeographed copy, 1949 september 7 (Folder 25)
          - "The United States and Democracy in Latin America," Typescript with cover memorandum, 1950 january 24 (Box 54, Folder 1)
          - "Political Factors of Latin America," Presentation at the U.S. Army Strategic Intelligence School. Memoranda, outlines, holograph drafts, 1951 february 1949-1951 (Folder 2)
        - Argentina
          - General
            - General. Source material
              - General, 1944-1946 (Folder 3)
                - Clippings
                - Wire reports
              - Internal conditions, 1930-1945 (Folder 4)
              - International relations. Clippings, dispatches, wire reports, notes, 1943-1951 (Folder 5)
            - Memoranda and correspondence, Includes draft sections of reports, 1945-1966 (Folder 6)
            - Notes and fragments, Includes outline for a study on communism, 1945-1948 (Folder 7)
          - "The Fascist-Totalitarian Character of the Present Argentine Regime," Mimeographed drafts and memorandum, 1944 october (Folder 8)
          - "Probable Lines of Development of Argentine Case at Mexico City," Typescript, circa 1945 (Folder 9)
          - "Internal Policies and Acts of the Argentine Government," Typescript, cover memorandum, letter from Nelson Rockefeller, 1945 June 26 (Folder 10)
          - Consultation Among the American Republics with Respect to the Argentine Situation, Draft materials, memorandum and two copies (one annotated) of mimeographed report, 1946 february (Folder 11)
          - "Present Controls Exercised by the Argentine Government," Mimeographed copy, 1946 october (Folder 12)
          - "The River Plate Bloc," Typescript, 1948 May (Folder 13)
          - "Trends in Southern South America," Typescript, 1948 august 25 (Folder 14)
        - Bolivia. Memorandum, clipping, and typescript report of an interview with Jose Antonio Arze, 1944-1956 (Folder 15)
        - Brazil. Unidentified holograph, memoranda, dispatches, 1945-1949 (Folder 16)
        - Chile. Notes, memoranda, dispatches, lecture transcript, letter, and short typescript reports relating primarily to the internal political situation, 1944-1955 (Folder 17)